I first became fascinated with octopus at an early age.
لقد فتنت بالأخطبوط في سن مبكرة
I grew up in Mobile, Alabama --
نشأت في موبايل, في ألاباما
somebody's got to be from Mobile, right? --
أحدهم يجب أن يكون من موبايل أليس كذلك ؟
and Mobile sits at the confluence of five rivers,
وتقع موبايل عند نقطة التقاء خمسة أنهار
forming this beautiful delta.
مكونة دلتا خلابة
And the delta has alligators crawling
ويوجد في الدلتا تماسيح تزحف
in and out of rivers filled with fish
تدخل وتخرج من أنهار ملئت بالأسماك
and cypress trees dripping with snakes,
وأشجار سرو مليئة بالأسماك
birds of every flavor.
طيور من جميع الأشكال
It's an absolute magical wonderland to live in --
إنها حتماً منطقة عجائب سحرية للعيش فيها
if you're a kid interested in animals, to grow up in.
خاصةً إذا كنت طفلا يود أن يكبر ليصبح حيوان
And this delta water flows to Mobile Bay, and finally into the Gulf of Mexico.
وهذا الدلتا تتدفق مياهها إلى خليج الموبايل وأخيرا إلى خليج المكسيك
And I remember my first real contact with octopus
وأتذكر أول اتصال حقيقي لي مع الأخطبوط
was probably at age five or six.
كان تقريبا في سن الخامسة أو السادسة
I was in the gulf, and I was swimming around and saw a little octopus on the bottom.
كنت في الخليج وكنت أسبح ورأيت أخطبوطا صغيرا في القاع
And I reached down and picked him up, and immediately
ونزلت للأسفل وأمسكت به وفي الحال
became fascinated and impressed by its speed and its strength and agility.
صرت مفتونا وأعجبت بسرعته وقوته وخفة حركته
It was prying my fingers apart and moving to the back of my hand.
كان يبتعد عن أصابعي ويتحرك بإتجاه خلفية رأسي
It was all I could do to hold onto this amazing creature.
هذا كان كل ما أستطيع أن أقوم به لكي أتمسك بهذا الكائن العجيب
Then it sort of calmed down in the palms of my hands
وبعدها بدأ بالهدوء نوعا ما في كف يدي
and started flashing colors,
وبدأ يضئ الألوان
just pulsing all of these colors.
فقط ومضات من هذه الألوان
And as I looked at it, it kind of tucked its arms under it,
وعندما نظرت إليه, كنت قد بدأت الامس أذرعه من الاسفل
raised into a spherical shape
ومن ثم رفعته على شكل دائري
and turned chocolate brown with two white stripes.
وتحول للون البني كلون الشوكولاته وبه خطان أبيضان
I'm going, "My gosh!" I had never seen anything like this in my life!
وقلت "يا إلهي" لم يسبق لي أن رأيت شيئا كهذا أبدا في حياتي
So I marveled for a moment, and then decided it was time to release him,
ذهلت للحظة ولكن قررت أنه حان الوقت لإطلاق سراحه
so I put him down.
لذا وضعته تحت
The octopus left my hands and then did the damnedest thing:
الأخطبوط ترك يدي ثم قام بشئ لم أتعجب منه
It landed on the bottom in the rubble
حل على كومة من الحصى
and -- fwoosh! -- vanished
وثم "فوووووششش" واختفى
right before my eyes.
على مرأى من عيني
And I knew, right then, at age six,
وعرفت عندها وأنا في السادسة من عمري
that is an animal that I want to learn more about. So I did.
أن هذا الحيوان, أريد أن أتعلم المزيد عنه. وفعلت
And I went off to college and got a degree in marine zoology,
وذهب للكلية وحصلت على شهادتي في علم الحيوان البحري
and then moved to Hawaii and entered graduate school
ومن ثم إنتقلت الى هاواي
at the University of Hawaii.
في جامعة هاواي
And while a student at Hawaii, I worked at the Waikiki Aquarium.
وبينما كنت طالبا في هاواي, عملت في حوض وايكيكي المائي
And the aquarium had a lot of big fish tanks
وكانت توجد أحواض سمك كبيرة في هذا الأكويريم
but not a lot of invertebrate displays,
ولكن لم يعرض الكثير من اللافقريات
and being the spineless guy, I thought, well
وكوني ذو الشخصية الضعيفة, فكرت في نفسي وقلت
I'll just go out in the field and collect these wonderful animals
سأذهب للميدان وأجمع هذه الحيوانات العجيبة
I had been learning about as a student
التي درست عنها بينما كنت طالبا
and bring them in, and I built these elaborate sets and put them on display.
وأحضرهم إلى هنا. فبنيت تلك المجموعات ووضعتها للعرض
Now, the fish in the tanks were gorgeous to look at,
الان, الأسماك الموجودة في الأحواض كبيرة جدا للنظر إليها
but they didn't really interact with people.
ولكن لا تتفاعل مع الأشخاص
But the octopus did.
ولكن الأخطبوط تفاعل
If you walked up to an octopus tank,
إذا مشيت لحوض الأخطبوط
especially early in the morning before anyone arrived,
خاضة في الصباح الباكر قبل مجئ أي شخص أخر
the octopus would rise up and look at you
فإن الأخطبوط سيرتفع وينظر إليك
and you're thinking, "Is that guy really looking at me? He is looking at me!"
وتفكر, أحقا هذا الرجل ينظر إلي؟ إنه ينظر إلي
And you walk up to the front of the tank. Then you realize
وتمشي إلى مقدمة الحوض, وتكتشف
that these animals all have different personalities:
أن هذه الحيوانات لها شخصيات مختلفة جميعها
Some of them would hold their ground,
بعضها ترسخ موقفها
others would slink into the back of the tank and disappear in the rocks,
وآخرون ينسلون خلسة الى الجزء الخلفي من الحوض وتختفي في الصخور.
and one in particular, this amazing animal ...
وواحدة بالتحديد, هذا الحيوان الرائع
I went up to the front of the tank, and he's just staring at me,
توجهت لمقدمة الحوض, وهو هناك ينظر إلي
and he had little horns come up above his eyes.
كان لديه قرون صغيرة تخرج عند عينيه
So I went right up to the front of the tank --
فذهبت لمقدمة الحوض
I was three or four inches from the front glass --
كنت على بعد ٣ أو ٤ بوصة عن الزجاج الأمامي
and the octopus was sitting on a perch, a little rock,
والأخطبوط كان جالسا على جثم, حصاة صغيرة
and he came off the rock and he also came down right to the front of the glass.
ونزل عن الحصاة وجاء كذلك لمقدمة الزجاج
So I was staring at this animal about six or seven inches away,
وها أنا أحدق على هذا الحيوان الذي يبعد حوالي ٦ أو ٧ بوصة عني
and at that time I could actually focus that close;
وفي ذلك الوقت كنت أستطيع أن أركز بذلك القرب
now as I look at my fuzzy fingers I realize those days are long gone.
الان عندما أنظر إلى أصابعي الغير واضحة, أكتشف أن هذه الأيام ولت منذ زمن بعيد
Anyway, there we were, staring at each other,
على العموم, ها نحن نحدق في بعضنا البعض
and he reaches down and grabs an armful of gravel
ويصل للأسفل ويتناول قطعا من الحصى ملئ اليد
and releases it in the jet of water entering the tank
ويطلقه بقوة بينما يدخل إلى الحوض
from the filtration system,
من خلال نظام التصفية
and -- chk chk chk chk chk! -- this gravel hits the front of the glass and falls down.
و "تشك تشك تشك تشك" الحصى يرتطم بالزجاج ويسقط مرة اخرى
He reaches up, takes another armful of gravel, releases it --
يرتفع مرة اخرى, يأخذ حصى ملئ ذراعه ويطلقه مرة اخرى
chk chk chk chk chk! -- same thing.
"تشك تشك تشك تشك" نفس الشئ
Then he lifts another arm and I lift an arm.
وثم يرفع يده, فأرفع أنا يدي كذلك
Then he lifts another arm and I lift another arm.
ثم يرفع يده الأخرى, وأرفع أنا يدي الأخرى كذلك
And then I realize the octopus won the arms race,
وثم ألاحظ أن الأخطبوط فاز في مسابقة رفع اليد
because I was out and he had six left. (Laughter)
لأنه لديه ست أيدي وأنا نفدت أيدي
But the only way I can describe what I was seeing that day
ولكن الطريقة الوحيدة التي أستطيع أن أصف فيها ما كنت أرى هو
was that this octopus was playing,
أن الأخطبوط كان يلعب
which is a pretty sophisticated behavior for a mere invertebrate.
والذي يعتبر تصرف نادر لمجردي اللافقاريات
So, about three years into my degree,
حسنا, حوالي ٣ سنوات في طور شهادتي
a funny thing happened on the way to the office,
شيء مضحك حصل لي في طريقي للمكتب
which actually changed the course of my life.
والذي غير مجرى حياتي تماما
A man came into the aquarium. It's a long story, but essentially
دخل رجل لمجمع حوض السمك, قصة طويلة ولكن أساسا
he sent me and a couple of friends of mine to the South Pacific
أرسل لي بعض أصحابي لجنوب المحيط الهادئ ،
to collect animals for him,
لجمع الحيوانات له ،
and as we left, he gave us two 16-millimeter movie cameras.
وبينما كنا ذاهبين, أعطانا فيديو كاميرتان بحجم ١٦ مم
He said, "Make a movie about this expedition."
وقال: "قوموا بعمل فيلم لهذه البعثة"
"OK, a couple of biologists making a movie --
حسنا, بعض البيولوجيون يقومون بعمل فيلم
this'll be interesting,"
هذا سيكون ممتعا
and off we went. And we did, we made a movie,
وانطلقنا, وبالفعل قمنا بتصوير الفيلم
which had to be the worst movie ever made
والذي كان بلا شك أسوأ فيلم تم تصويره على الإطلاق
in the history of movie making,
في تاريخ الأفلام
but it was a blast. I had so much fun.
ولكننا استمتعنا كثيرا. كان أكثر من رائع
And I remember that proverbial light going off in my head,
واتذكر ذلك "الضوء" الذي يضرب به المثل يضئ في رأسي
thinking, "Wait a minute.
يفكر: "انتظر لحظة"
Maybe I can do this all the time.
"ربما أستطيع القيام بهذا طوال الوقت"
Yeah, I'll be a filmmaker."
"نعم, سوف أكون مخرج"
So I literally came back from that job,
لذا, رجعت فعليا من ذلك العمل
quit school, hung my filmmaking shingle
تركت المدرسة, وعلقت لوحتي الخشبية للإخراج
and just never told anyone that I didn't know what I was doing.
ولكني لم أخبر أحدا أبدا بأني لا علم لدي عن ماذا أقوم به
It's been a good ride.
لقد كانت رحلة جيدة
And what I learned in school though was really beneficial.
والذي تعلمته في المدرسة في الواقع كان مفيدا للغاية
If you're a wildlife filmmaker
إذا كنت صانع أفلام للحياة البرية
and you're going out into the field to film animals,
وتخرج للميدان لتصور الحيوانات
especially behavior,
وبالأخص سلوكهم
it helps to have a fundamental background
فإنه يساعدك أن تكون لديك خلفية أساسية
on who these animals are,
عن من هم هذه الحيوانات
how they work and, you know, a bit about their behaviors.
كيف يعملون, وتعلمون, القليل عن سلوكياتهم كذلك
But where I really learned about octopus
ولكن المكان الذي تعلمت فيه عن الأخطبوط
was in the field, as a filmmaker
كان في عالم تصوير الأفلام
making films with them,
بينما كنت أصورهم
where you're allowed to spend large periods of time
عندما يسمح لك بأن تمضي وقتا طويلا معهم
with the animals, seeing octopus being octopus
تشاهد الأخطبوط كأخطبوط
in their ocean homes.
في عالم المحيطات الخاص بهم
I remember I took a trip to Australia,
أتذكر, ذهبت في رحلة إلى أستراليا
went to an island called One Tree Island.
ذهبت لجزيرة إسمها "جزيرة الشجرة الوحيدة
And apparently, evolution had occurred
و على ما يبدو ، قد حدث تطور
at a pretty rapid rate on One Tree,
بشكل سريع في "الشجرة الوحيدة"
between the time they named it and the time I arrived,
في خلال الوقت الذي تم تسميتها حتى الوقت الذي وصلت فيه
because I'm sure there were at least three trees
لأنني متأكد بأنه هناك ما لا يقل عن ٣ شجرات على الأقل
on that island when we were there.
على تلك الجزيرة عندما كنا هناك
Anyway, one tree is situated right next to
على العموم, شجرة واحدة متواجدة بالقرب من
a beautiful coral reef.
شعب مرجانية جميلة
In fact, there's a surge channel
في الواقع, هناك قناة إندفاع
where the tide is moving back and forth, twice a day, pretty rapidly.
حيث التيار ينتقل إلى الأمام وإلى الخلف, مرتين يومين, بسرعة نوعا ما
And there's a beautiful reef,
وهناك شعب جميلة
very complex reef, with lots of animals,
معقدة كثيرا وبها الكثير من الحيوانات
including a lot of octopus.
بالإضافة للكثير من الأخطبوطات
And not uniquely
ولم يكن فريدا
but certainly, the octopus in Australia
ولكن قطعا, الأخطبوط في أستراليا
are masters at camouflage.
هو متمكن من التمويه جدا
As a matter of fact,
كما في واقع الأمر
there's one right there.
يوجد واحد هنا
So our first challenge was to find these things,
لذا, فإن تحدينا الأول هو أن نجد هذه الأشياء
and that was a challenge, indeed.
وهذه كانت التحديات بالفعل
But the idea is, we were there for a month
ولكن الفكرة كانت على أساس أننا سنكون هناك لمدة شهر فقط
and I wanted to acclimate the animals to us
وأردت من الحيوانات أن تتأقلم لوجودنا
so that we could see behaviors without disturbing them.
من أجل أن نستطيع أن نرى سلوكياتهم دون أن نزعجهم
So the first week was pretty much spent
لذا, فإن الأسبوع الأول تم تمضيته نوعا ما
just getting as close as we could,
بأن نحاول أن نتقرب منهم قدر المستطاع
every day a little closer, a little closer, a little closer.
كل يوم كنا نتقرب أكثر قليلا, وقليلا وقليلا
And you knew what the limit was: they would start getting twitchy
وتعرفون ماذا كان الحد لنا؟ كانوا يبدأون بالإضطراب
and you'd back up, come back in a few hours.
وعندها تعلم أن عليك الذهاب والرجوع بعد بضع ساعات
And after the first week, they ignored us.
ونعود بعد أسبوع ونجد بأنهم تجاهلونا
It was like, "I don't know what that thing is, but he's no threat to me."
كان كأنهم يقولون: "لا أعرف ما هو هذا الشئ ولكنهم ليسوا بمثابة خطر لنا"
So they went on about their business
فانطلقوا لقضاء أعمالهم
and from a foot away, we're watching mating
ومن على بعد قدم كنا نراهم يتزاوجون
and courting and fighting
ويتغازلون ويتشاجرون
and it is just an unbelievable experience.
وكانت تجربة لا توصف
And one of the most fantastic displays
وأحد أروع المناظر التي
that I remember, or at least visually,
أتذكرها, أو على الأقل بصريا
was a foraging behavior.
كان تصرفهم للبحث عن المؤونة
And they had a lot of different techniques
وكانت لديهم تقنيات مختلفة
that they would use for foraging,
كانوا يستخدمونها للبحث
but this particular one used vision.
ولكن هذه بالذات كانوا يستخدمون البصر فيها
And they would see a coral head,
كانوا يرون الشعب أمامهم
maybe 10 feet away,
ربما على بعد عشر أقدام
and start moving over toward that coral head.
ويبدأون بالتحرك تجاه قمة الشعب
And I don't know whether they actually saw crab in it, or imagined that one might be,
ولا أعلم هل رأوا سلطعون فيها أو تخيلوا أن يتواجد فيها واحد
but whatever the case, they would leap off the bottom
ولكن مهما كانت القضية, كانوا يقفزون من الأسفل
and go through the water and land right on top of this coral head,
ويدخلون في الماء ويحلون فوق قمة الشعب
and then the web between the arms
ومن ثم فإن الشباك التي بين أذرعم ...
would completely engulf the coral head,
تنغمس في قمة الشعب
and they would fish out, swim for crabs.
ويغوصون بحثا عن السلطعونات
And as soon as the crabs touched the arm, it was lights out.
وبمجرد أن لمست السرطانات الذراع, كان كأنه تم إطفاء الأنوار.
And I always wondered what happened under that web.
وكنت أتساءل دائما ما الذي يحدث تحت تلك الشبكة
So we created a way to find out, (Laughter)
لذا, أخترعنا طريقة لنستكشف
and I got my first look at that famous beak in action.
وحصلت على أول نظرة على المنقار الشهير وهو في نطاق العمل.
It was fantastic.
كان رائعا
If you're going to make a lot of films about a particular group of animals,
إذا كنت تريد أن تقوم بأفلام كثيرة عن إحدى مجموعات الحيوانات
you might as well pick one that's fairly common.
فقد يكون من الأجدر أن تختار ما هو شائع لحد كبير
And octopus are, they live in all the oceans.
والأخطبوط هو كذلك, يعيشون في كل المحيطات
They also live deep.
ويعيشون في عمق غزير
And I can't say octopus are responsible
ولا أستطيع أن أقول أن الأخطبوط مسؤول عن
for my really strong interest
إهتمامي القوي
in getting in subs and going deep,
للغواصات والغوص في الأعماق
but whatever the case, I like that.
ولكن مهما كانت القضية, فإنها تعجبني
It's like nothing you've ever done.
إنه ليس كأي شئ قمت به من قبل
If you ever really want to get away from it all
إذا كنت فعلا تود أن تبتعد عن كل شئ
and see something that you have never seen,
وترى شيئا لم تشاهده أبدا
and have an excellent chance of seeing something
ويكون لديك فرصة ممتازة لمشاهدة شئ
no one has ever seen, get in a sub.
لم يره أحد, إدخل في داخل غواصة
You climb in, seal the hatch, turn on a little oxygen,
تركب, تغلق الفتحة, تدير الأكسجين قليلا
turn on the scrubber,
تدير هذا الجهاز لغسل الغاز
which removes the CO2 in the air you breathe, and they chuck you overboard.
الذي يزيل ثاني أكسيد الكربون الذي يخرج من خلال التنفس, ويخرجونه للخارج
Down you go. There's no connection to the surface
وتنزلون. لا يوجد هناك إتصال بالسطح الخارجي
apart from a pretty funky radio.
سوى راديو غريب
And as you go down, the washing machine
بينما تنزلون, الغسالة في
at the surface calms down.
السطح تبدأ بالهدوء
And it gets quiet.
ومن ثم تهدأ
And it starts getting really nice.
ويكون الوضع جميلا جدا
And as you go deeper, that lovely, blue water you were launched in
بينما تنزلون في عمق أكثر, ذاك الماء الأزرق الذي نزلتم فيه
gives way to darker and darker blue.
يخرج درجات أعمق من الزرقة
And finally, it's a rich lavender,
ومن ثم يكون ليلكي غامق
and after a couple of thousand feet, it's ink black.
ومن ثم, بعد بضع ألف قدم, يكون أسود قاتم
And now you've entered the realm
والان تكونون دخلتوا عالم اخر
of the mid-water community.
من مجتمع وسط المياه
You could give an entire talk
بإمكانك أن تقوم بإلقاء محاضرة بأكملها
about the creatures that live in the mid-water.
عن الكائنات التي تعيش في منتصف المياه
Suffice to say though, as far as I'm concerned,
يكفينا القول, بقدر ما أنا مهتم
without question, the most bizarre designs
أنه, بدون سؤال, من أغرب التصاميم على الإطلاق
and outrageous behaviors
ومن السلوكيات المشينة
are in the animals that live in the mid-water community.
هي الحيوانات التي تعيش في هذه المنطقة من منتصف المياه
But we're just going to zip right past this area,
ولكننا سننتقل بسرعة في هذه المنطقة
this area that includes about 95 percent
هذه المنطقة التي تحتوي حوالي ٩٥٪
of the living space on our planet
من الكائنات الحية في عالمنا
and go to the mid-ocean ridge, which I think is even more extraordinary.
وانتقل إلى جبل في وسط المحيط ، وهو ما أعتقد أنه أكثر استثنائية.
The mid-ocean ridge is a huge mountain range,
عالم وسط المحيطات هي سلسلة جبال هائلة
40,000 miles long, snaking around the entire globe.
طولها 40،000 ميلا، متعرجة في كل العالم.
And they're big mountains, thousands of feet tall,
وهناك جبال كبيرة، علوها آلالاف الأقدام،
some of which are tens of thousands of feet
وبعض منها تعلو عشرات الآلاف من الأقدام
and bust through the surface,
وتبرز عبر السطح،
creating islands like Hawaii.
خالقة جزر مثل هاواي.
And the top of this mountain range
وأعلى هذه السلسلة الجبلية
is splitting apart, creating a rift valley.
منقسم ، مكوناً وادي متصدع.
And when you dive into that rift valley, that's where the action is
وعندما تغطس داخل الوادي المتصدع، هناك يكمن الحراك
because literally thousands of active volcanoes
لأنه، حرفياً، آلالاف من البراكين النشطة
are going off at any point in time
قد تنفجر في أي لحظة من الزمن،
all along this 40,000 mile range.
على طول هذه ال 40،000 ميلاً.
And as these tectonic plates are spreading apart,
وبينما تنبسط هذه الصفائح التكتونية بعيدا
magma, lava is coming up and filling those gaps,
تأتي الحمم والصخور لتسد تلك الثغرات.
and you're looking land -- new land --
وتنظر أنت للأرض، أرض جديدة،
being created right before your eyes.
يتم تشكيلها تماماً أمام ناظريك.
And over the tops of them is 3,000 to 4,000 meters of water
وعلى قممها ثلاث إلى أربع آلالاف متر من الماء،
creating enormous pressure,
تخلق ضغوطاً هائلة،
forcing water down through the cracks toward the center of the earth,
كابحة الماء لأسفل عبر الشقوق نحو مركز الأرض
until it hits a magma chamber
حتى تضرب غرفة الإنصهار،
where it becomes superheated
حيث تصبح حارة للغاية
and supersaturated with minerals,
ومشبعة جداً بالمعادن،
reverses its flow and starts shooting back to the surface
وتعكس إتجاه سريانها وتبدأ بقصف الحمم تجاه السطح،
and is ejected out of the earth like a geyser at Yellowstone.
وتخرج إلى الأرض مثل السخان في يلوستون.
In fact, this whole area
في الواقع، كل هذه المنطقة
is like a Yellowstone National Park with all of the trimmings.
مثل حديقة يلوستون الوطنية مع كل الزركشة.
And this vent fluid is about 600 or 700 degrees F.
وهذا التنفيس عبر السائل يصل لحوالي ستمائة أو 700 درجة فهرنهايت.
The surrounding water is just a couple of degrees above freezing.
بينما المياه المحيطة بها ليست سوى بضع درجات فوق الصفر.
So it immediately cools,
ولهذا تبرد في الحال،
and it can no longer hold in suspension
ولا تستطيع بعد تحمّل كل
all of the material that it's dissolved,
هذه المعادن التي تحللت،
and it precipitates out, forming black smoke.
فتترسب ، مشكلّةً دخان أسود.
And it forms these towers, these chimneys
وتقوم بتشكيل هذه الأبراج، هذه المداخن
that are 10, 20, 30 feet tall.
التي تعلو 10 إلى 30 قدماً.
And all along the sides of these chimneys
وعلى جانبي كل من هذه المداخن
is shimmering with heat and loaded with life.
وميض من الحرارة معبّق بالحياة.
You've got black smokers going all over the place
فتحصل على دخاخين سوداء تلف المكان
and chimneys that have tube worms
ومداخن لها أنابيب ملتوية
that might be eight to 10 feet long.
التي قد تكون 8 إلى 10 أقدام في الطول.
And out of the tops of these tube worms
وخارج قمم هذه الأنابيب الملتوية
are these beautiful red plumes.
توجد هذه الأعمدة الحمراء الجميلة.
And living amongst the tangle of tube worms
وتعيش بينها كومة الأنابيب الملتوية
is an entire community of animals:
مجتمع كامل من الحيوانات،
shrimp, fish, lobsters, crab,
الجمبري، السمك، جراد البحر، سرطان البحر ،
clams and swarms of arthropods
المحار واسراب من المفصليات
that are playing that dangerous game
إنهم يلعبون تلك اللعبة الخطرة
between over here is scalding hot and freezing cold.
بين مياة ساخنة حد الموت وباردة حد التجمد.
And this whole ecosystem
وكل هذا النظام البيئي
wasn't even known about
لم يكن معروفاً قبل حوالي
until 33 years ago.
33 عاماً مضت.
And it completely threw science on its head.
وقد قلب العلم رأساً على عقب.
It made scientists rethink
وقد جعل العلماء يعيدون التفكير
where life on Earth might have actually begun.
من أين قد بدأت الحياة على الأرض بالفعل.
And before the discovery of these vents,
وقبل إكتشاف هذه المخارج،
all life on Earth, the key to life on Earth,
كل الحياة على الأرض، مفاتيح الحياة على الأرض،
was believed to be the sun and photosynthesis.
كان يعتقد أنها الشمس والتمثيل الضوئي،
But down there, there is no sun,
لكن في تلك المنطقة، لا توجد شمس،
there is no photosynthesis;
و لا يوجد تمثيل ضوئي.
it's chemosynthetic environment down there driving it,
إنها بيئة تخليق كيميائي موجودة هناك،
and it's all so ephemeral.
وكلها سريعة الزوال.
You might film this
ربما تصورون هذا
unbelievable hydrothermal vent,
فوهات الماء التي لا تصدق،
which you think at the time has to be on another planet.
التي تعتقدون أنها من كوكب آخر.
It's amazing to think that this is actually on earth;
من المدهش أن نفكر بأنها فعلاً على كوكب الأرض.
it looks like aliens in an alien environment.
وهي تبدو مثل الغرباء في بيئة غريبة.
But you go back to the same vent eight years later
لكنك تعود لنفس الفوهة بعد ثمان سنوات،
and it can be completely dead.
وقد تجدها ميتة تماماً.
There's no hot water.
لا توجد مياه حارة
All of the animals are gone, they're dead,
وأندثرت كل الحيوانات وماتت.
and the chimneys are still there
وكل المداخن ما تزال هناك
creating a really nice ghost town,
صانعة مدينة أشباح رائعة،
an eerie, spooky ghost town,
مدينة أشباح مخيفة جداً،
but essentially devoid of animals, of course.
لكنها تخلو من الحيوانات بالطبع.
But 10 miles down the ridge...
لكن على بعد 10 أميال أسفل التلال...
pshhh! There's another volcano going.
بشششش! هناك بركان آخر يغلي.
And there's a whole new hydrothermal vent community that has been formed.
وهناك مجتمع جديد كلياً تم تشكيله على فوهة المياه الحارة.
And this kind of life and death of hydrothermal vent communities
وهذا النوع من الحياة والموت للمجتمعات المائية
is going on every 30 or 40 years
يحدث كل 30 أو 40 سنة
all along the ridge.
على طول التلال.
And that ephemeral nature
وتلك الطبيعة سريعة الزوال
of the hydrothermal vent community
لمجتمع فوهات المياة الحارة
isn't really different from some of the
لا يختلف في الحقيقة من
areas that I've seen
بعض المناطق التي رأيتها
in 35 years of traveling around, making films.
طوال 35 عاماً من التجوال وصنع الأفلام.
Where you go and film a really nice sequence at a bay.
حيث تذهب وتصوّر سلسلة رائعة حقاً في الخليج.
And you go back, and I'm at home,
وتعود أدراجك، في البيت
and I'm thinking, "Okay, what can I shoot ...
أفكّر، " حسناً، ماذا يمكنني أن أرى.
Ah! I know where I can shoot that.
أه، أعرف أين سأصوّر ذلك.
There's this beautiful bay, lots of soft corals and stomatopods."
هناك خليج جميل، الكثير من الشعب الناعمة والرخويات.
And you show up, and it's dead.
وعندما تراها، إنها ميتة.
There's no coral, algae growing on it, and the water's pea soup.
لا توجد شعب مرجانية، نمت عليها الطحالب، و رغوة الماء.
You think, "Well, what happened?"
ثم تفكّر، " حسناً، مالذي حدث؟"
And you turn around,
وتجول المكان،
and there's a hillside behind you with a neighborhood going in,
ثم تجد جبلاً خلفك حيّ يتم بناؤه،
and bulldozers are pushing piles of soil back and forth.
والجرافات تدفع بالتراب ذهاباً وإياباً.
And over here
وهناك
there's a golf course going in.
يتم بناء ملعب للغولف.
And this is the tropics.
وتلك المدارات.
It's raining like crazy here.
تمطر بجنون هنا.
So this rainwater is flooding down the hillside,
إذاً فهذه المياه تتدفق إلى أسفل التل،
carrying with it sediments from the construction site,
حاملة معها رواسب موقع البناء،
smothering the coral and killing it.
فتختق الشعب المرجانية وتقتلها.
And fertilizers and pesticides
والأسمدة والمبيدات الحشرية
are flowing into the bay from the golf course --
تتدفق إلى الخليج من ملعب الغولف.
the pesticides killing all the larvae and little animals,
تقتل المبيدات كل اليرقات والحيوانات الصغيرة،
fertilizer creating this beautiful plankton bloom --
وتصنع الأسمدة هذه العوالق المزهرة.
and there's your pea soup.
ويوجد حساء البازلا خاصتك.
But, encouragingly, I've seen just the opposite.
لكن ما يبعث على التشجيع. أنني رأيت العكس.
I've been to a place that was a pretty trashed bay.
لقد ذهبت لمكان كان مثل مكب نفايات الخليج.
And I looked at it, just said, "Yuck,"
ونظرت له وقلت ، "مكان قذر"
and go and work on the other side of the island.
لأذهب وأعمل على الجزء الآخر من الجزيرة.
Five years later, come back,
بعد خمس سنوات، عدت،
and that same bay is now gorgeous. It's beautiful.
ونفس الخليج الآن فاتن وجميل.
It's got living coral, fish all over the place,
فيه شعب مرجانية حية، أسماك في كل مكان،
crystal clear water, and you go, "How did that happen?"
مياه نقية وصافية، وتتساءل "مالذي حدث؟"
Well, how it happened is
حسناً، ما حدث هو أن
the local community galvanized.
المجتمع المحلي قد تعافى.
They recognized what was happening on the hillside and put a stop to it;
لقد وعوا لما يحدث على جانب التل وأوقفوه،
enacted laws and made permits required
سنوا قوانين وطالبوا برخصة
to do responsible construction
لبناء مباني مسئولة
and golf course maintenance
وصيانة لملعب الغولف
and stopped the sediments flowing into the bay,
وتوقفت الرواسب من التدفق إلى الخليج،
and stopped the chemicals flowing into the bay,
وتوقفوا عن رمي المواد الكيميائية في الخليج،
and the bay recovered.
وقد تعافى الخليج.
The ocean has an amazing ability
لدى المحيط مقدرة مدهشة
to recover, if we'll just leave it alone.
على التعافي، إذا تركناه بدون أذى.
I think Margaret Mead
أعتقد أن مارغريت ميد
said it best.
قالتها بصورة أفضل.
She said that a small group of thoughtful people
لقد قالت أن مجموعة صغيرة من المفكرين
could change the world.
تستطيع تغيير العالم.
Indeed, it's the only thing that ever has.
بالطبع، إنه الشئ الوحيد الذي لدينا.
And a small group of thoughtful people
مجموعة صغيرة من المفكرين
changed that bay.
غيروا ذلك الخليج.
I'm a big fan of grassroots organizations.
أنا معجب كبير بالمنظمات الشعبية .
I've been to a lot of lectures
لقد حضرت الكثير من المحاضرات
where, at the end of it, inevitably,
حيث يكون أول سؤال في نهاية المحاضرة
one of the first questions that comes up is,
و لا يمكن تجنبه هو،
"But, but what can I do?
" لكن، مالذي أستطيع فعله؟
I'm an individual. I'm one person.
أنا فرد. أنا شخص واحد.
And these problems are so large and global, and it's just overwhelming."
وهذه المشاكل ضخمة جداً وذات طابع كوني، إنها مذهلة جداً."
Fair enough question.
سؤال ممتاز للغاية
My answer to that is don't look
وجوابي لذلك هو أن لا تنظر
at the big, overwhelming issues of the world.
للصورة الكبيرة والمذهلة للعالم.
Look in your own backyard.
أنظر للفناء الخلفي خاصتك.
Look in your heart, actually.
أنظر في دواخلك، قلبك.
What do you really care about that isn't right where you live?
ما تحتاج حقاً لتهتم به هو حيث تعيش بالضبط
And fix it.
وقم بإصلاحه.
Create a healing zone in your neighborhood
أصنع منطقة تعافي في حيّك السكني
and encourage others to do the same.
وشجّع الآخرين لفعل نفس الشئ.
And maybe these healing zones can sprinkle a map,
وربما مناطق التعافي هذه يمكن أن ترسم على خارطة،
little dots on a map.
نقاط صغيرة على الخارطة.
And in fact, the way that we can communicate today --
وفي الواقع، عبر الطريقة التي نتواصل بها اليوم،
where Alaska is instantly knowing what's going on in China,
حيث تعرف ألاسكا على الفور ما يحدث في الصين،
and the Kiwis did this, and then over in England they tried to ...
ونيوزلاندا، وهناك في إنجلترا يحاولون أن...
and everybody is talking to everyone else --
ويتحدث الجميع مع بعضهم البعض.
it's not isolated points on a map anymore,
لم تعد نقاط متفرقة على الخارطة بتاتاً،
it's a network we've created.
إنها شبكة قمنا نحن بصنعها.
And maybe these healing zones can start growing,
وربما تبدأ مناطق التعافي هذه في الإزدياد،
and possibly even overlap, and good things can happen.
وربما تتقاطع، وتحدث الأشياء الجيدة.
So that's how I answer that question.
وهكذا أقوم بالإجابة على السؤال.
Look in your own backyard, in fact, look in the mirror.
أنظر لفناءك الخلفي، وأنظر في المرآة.
What can you do that is more responsible
مالذي تستطيع فعله بمسئولية أكثر
than what you're doing now?
مما تفعله الآن؟
And do that, and spread the word.
وقم بفعل ذلك. وأنشروا الوعي.
The vent community animals
لا يستطيع مجتمع حيوانات الفوهات
can't really do much
فعل الكثير
about the life and death
حيال الحياة والموت
that's going on where they live, but up here we can.
التي تجري حيث يقطنون، لكننا نحن نستطيع.
In theory, we're thinking, rational human beings.
نظرياً، نحن نفكر بعقلانية البشر.
And we can make changes to our behavior
ويمكننا تغيير سلوكنا
that will influence and affect the environment,
الذي سيؤثر على البيئة،
like those people changed the health of that bay.
مثل أؤلئك الناس الذين غيّروا صحة المياه في الخليج.
Now, Sylvia's TED Prize wish
الآن، أمنية سيلفيا لجائزة تيد
was to beseech us to do anything we could,
كانت تطلب منا فعل أي شئ نستطيع،
everything we could,
أي شئ نستطيع فعله،
to set aside not pin pricks,
لنتعاون، لا أن نتفرق،
but significant expanses
بمساحات ملحوظة
of the ocean for preservation,
للحفاظ على المحيطات،
"hope spots," she calls them.
"نقاط الأمل" كما تسميها.
And I applaud that. I loudly applaud that.
وقد حييّت ذلك. أنا أحيّ ذلك بصوت عال.
And it's my hope that some of these "hope spots"
وأملي أن بعض نقاط الأمل هذه
can be in the deep ocean,
يمكن أن تكون في أعماق المحيط،
an area that has historically
المناطق المهملة عبر التاريخ
been seriously neglected, if not abused.
إن لم تكن يساء معاملتها --
The term "deep six" comes to mind:
قفز مصطلح العمق (36 قدماً) إلى ذهني.
"If it's too big or too toxic for a landfill,
إذا كانت ضخمة أو سامة جداً للأرض،
deep six it!"
أدفنها على عمق 36 قدماً.
So, I hope that we can also keep
لذا، أرجو أن نستطيع أيضاً المحافظة
some of these "hope spots" in the deep sea.
على بعض نقاط الأمل هذه في أعماق البحار.
Now, I don't get a wish,
الآن ليس لدي أمنية،
but I certainly can say
لكني بالتأكيد أستطيع القول
that I will do anything I can
أنني سأبذل قصارى جهدي
to support Sylvia Earle's wish.
لدعم تحقيق أمنية سيلفيا إيرلي.
And that I do.
وأنني سأفعل ذلك.
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكراً جزيلاً. (تصفيق)